Guide to the Charles W. Ranson Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Charles W. Ranson Papers
1938-1979
RG 96
Yale University Divinity School Library
9
(18 boxes)
This record group documents Ranson's mission and ecumenical work, particularly providing insight on the development and operations of the International Missionary Council and Theological Education Fund. His work as a theological educator and administrator, and his latter years in a Congregational pastorate are also documented. Ranson served as an Irish Methodist missionary in South India, General Secretary of the International Missionary Council, Director of the Theological Education Fund and Dean of the Drew University Theological School.
Ranson, Charles W., 1903-1988
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Ranson family.
Biographical / Historical
1903 Jun 15 Born in Ballyclure, Northern Ireland, son of the Rev. Henry John Fredrick and Elizabeth (Clarke) Ranson.
19xx Educated at Queens University and Edgehill Theological College, Belfast, and Oriel College, Oxford.
1929 Ordained to ministry of Methodist Church in Ireland.
1929-1943 Missionary, Madras, So. India; chaplain to the Viceroy and Governor General of India.
1932 Married Jessie Grace Margaret Gibb (d. 1957). Children: Mary Elizabeth, John Hugh, Kathleen Anne.
1937 Published A City in Transition
1940 Published The Things that Abide
1943-1945 Secretary, National Christian Council of India, Burma, and Ceylon
1945 Published The Christian Minister in India
1946-1947 Research Secretary, International Missionary Council, London
1948-1958 General Secretary, International Missionary Council
1952 D.Th, University of Kiel, Germany
1953 Published That the World May Know
1958-1964 Director, Theological Education Fund
1961-1962 President of the Methodist Church in Ireland
1962 Married Barbara B. Hicks
1962-1968 Professor of Ecumenical Theology, Drew University Theological School
1963-1967 Jan Dean, Drew Theological School
1968-1972 Professor of Theology and Ecumenics, Hartford Seminary Foundation
1971-1975 Pastor, Congregational Church, Salisbury, CT
1988 Died
Scope and Contents
These papers document Ranson's work for ecumenical mission organizations, his work as a theological educator and administrator, and his latter years in a Congregational pastorate. Printed materials and correspondence with individuals such as John R. Mott and John Mackay shed light on the operations and development of the ecumenical missions enterprise, particularly the International Missionary Council and the Theological Education Fund of the World Council of Churches.
The correspondence of Series I is divided into three subsections, reflecting Ranson's system of filing. The Alphabetical Sequence primarily covers the years up to 1967 while the Chronological Sequence covers the years from 1967 to 1979. A Topical Sequence primarily relates to Ranson's speaking and writing engagements. Correspondence related to Ranson's address to the World Council of Churches meeting in Evanston in 1954 has been filed with that address in Series II, Writings. A significant portion of Ranson's professional correspondence is contained in Series V, Organizations Served, particularly in the files for Drew University, the Hartford Seminary Foundation, the Irish Methodist Church, and the Theological Education Fund.
The Writings of Series II are divided into two sections: Articles and Lectures/Sermons. These writings include both published and unpublished material. They are complemented by the Travel Diaries and Notes of Series III, which primarily relate to Ranson's work with the International Missionary Council, and the Notes of Series IV, which primarily relate to his work as a professor.
Series V, Organizations Served, contains a great deal of valuable documentation about the operations and policy of the church and educational organizations that Ranson led. The Yale Divinity Library holds complementary archival material for many of the missions and ecumenical organization with which Ranson was involved.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings
III. Travel Diaries / Notes
IV. Notes
V. Organizations Served
VI. Biographical Documentation
VII. Collected Material
Methodist Church -- Ireland; Ecumenists; Educators; Missionaries -- India; Mackay, John Alexander, 1889-1983; Mott, John R. (John Raleigh), 1865-1955; Ranson, Charles W., 1903-1988; Drew University. Theological School; International Missionary Council; Theological Education Fund
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Alphabetical sequence
    - A, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Albright, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Appleton, George, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - B, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bingle, Ernest, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Boegner, Marc, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Boston University, School of Theology, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - C, 1953,1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Campbell, Beatrice, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Christian Albrechts Universitat in Kiel, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Cline, Myrtle, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Chitterbuck, Basil -- See: Methodist Missionary Society
    - Cochrane, Robert, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Cochrane, Thomas, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Craig, A.C., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Davis, J. Merle, 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Decker, John William, 1949-1957, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Dickinson College, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Dixon, Stanley, 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Drew University, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Fagley, Richard -- See: Nolde, O.F. Sep 28, 1950
    - First Name Only, 1949-1961, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - G, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Goodall, Norman, 1945-1952 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - H, 1956, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Hoffman, Conrad, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Hogg, W. Richey, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Harper, J., 1952 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Hartford Seminary Foundation, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - International Missionary Council, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Johnson, Alfred, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - K, 1952,1967 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Kennard, Mrs. Spencer, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Kidd, A.S., 1948 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Latourette, Kenneth S., 1950 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Leiper, Henry, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Long, Charles, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Lux Mundi, 1967, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Mackay, John Alexander, 1949-1952 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Mackie, Robert, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Manikam, Dr. and Mrs. Rajan, 1940, 1950, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - McLeish, Alexander, 1948, 1950, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Mott, John R., 1948-1952 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Methodist Missionary Society, 1945-1967 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Neilson, Erik W., 1950 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Nolde, O.F., 1950 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Norris, Marion, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Oldham, J.H., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Pusey, Nathan M., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Rankin, M. Theron, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Ranson Children: Mary Elizabeth; John Hugh; Kathleen Anne, 1948-1977, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Ranson, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - S, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Sockman, Ralph W., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Student Christian Movement, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - T, 1956, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Thompson, W. E. Morley; Methodist Church in Ireland, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - W, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Weddell, Sue, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Warnshuis, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Wysner, Gloria, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Topical sequence
    - Writing Assignments Declined, 1954-1966 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Writing Assignments Pending, 1961-1964, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Engagements Declined, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Engagements Pending, 1956-1967 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Writing Assignments Completed, 1954-1964 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Engagements Completed, 1952,1958 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Finance: Taxes and Pension, 1957-1963 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Christmas Cards, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Chronological sequence
    - Correspondence, 1967-1979 (Box 2, Folder 67-77)
- Writings, Series II
  - Articles
    - "India in Transition;" "Education and the Challenge of the Present Crisis;" "Jesus Christ, the Same Yesterday, and Today and Forever;" "Christian Witness in a Revolutionary World;" "Priorities in the World Mission of the Church;" "Faith for a World Community;" "Towards a Christian Strategy in East Asia;" "Missionary Freedom and the International Missionary Council;" "The Threat to Religious Liberty in Asia;" "Reformation: Old and New;" "Prejudice, History and Missions;" "The Gospel and the Church;""Missions Reshaping the World;""The World Mission at Mid-Century;""The New World Mission;""The Other End of the Road;""The World Church and the World Crisis;""We Intend to Go Together", 1938-1953 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - "Consider Africa;""The Missionary Calling;""The Gospel for This Generation;""The End of an Era;""Training National Leaders in India;""Latin America and the World Christian Fellowship", 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - "World Parish Notebook", 1955 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - "Challenge and Response;""The Missionary Obligation of the Church;""Leviathan of the South;""The Missionary Outreach of the 'Sects'";"Optimism of Grace;""Eternal Purpose and World Mission of the Church;", 1956 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - "World Church--Fact or Fiction?""John Alexander Mackay;""The Theological Education Fund;""The Growing Significance of Younger Churches and New Nations (Ch. 18)";"Foreword"; "Some Impressions of the Meeting of the Commission on World Mission and Evangelism;""The Anatomy of Revolution;""Leslie Newbigin: Bishop, Missionary and Apostle of Unity;""The Installation of the Rev. Charles W. Ranson as Dean of the Theological School -- Drew University", 1959-1965 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - "The Ministerial Vocation in Crisis;" Letter to All-Saints' Church;"Madras Revisited;" Entries:"Ecumenical Movement, Eucharist, Missions, Christian:""The Most Important Errand;""Missionary Frontiersmen;""Christian Witness in a Revolutionary World;""The World Task of Christian Education;""World-Wide Evangelism in this Generation;", 1966-1977, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Reviews by Ranson, 1954-1967, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Reviews of Ranson, 1945-1956 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Lectures, Sermons
    - Sermon Registry;"The Treasures of Darkness;""The Unchanging Christ;""Child Likeness;""The Contemporary Christ;""The Gifts of Pentecost;""The Eternal Christ;""Finding God;""What is Man?""The Divided Self;""Frustration and Fulfillment;""Day of Prayer for Navy and Merchant Service;""The Comfort of God;""The Ultimate Tragedy;""This is the Victory;""The Body of Christ;""I am a Debtor;""The Listening Ear;""The Heritage of Freedom;""Brother Christians;""The Grace of Our Lord Jesus Christ;""The Love of God;""The Communion of the Holy Ghost;""Total Victory", 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Sermon Notebook;"Finding God;""The Gift Perfect;""The Divided Self;""Frustration and Fulfillment;""The Triumph of Fulfillment;""The Sailor's Task and Ours;""The Comfort of God", 1942 (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Memorial Service for Reginald Dann;"The Salt of the Earth: Those Who Dream Dreams;" Guild of Service Meeting;"1914 and 1939 Then and Now;""Is War Inevitable?""Frustration and Fulfillment;""Jesus Christ, the Same Yesterday, Today and Forever;" Sermon Notebook;"Research as an Aid in Determining Mission Strategy;""World Without Books;" Address;"Towards a Missionary Strategy;""Armistice, 1948", 1939-1949 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Princeton University - The Annual Mission Lectures;Lectures at Drew University, 1948, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - "Sceptred Myths;""The Far East Over-All Picture -- New Strategy in Missions;""The Church and Her Mission;" Ecumenical Methodist Conference; Commencement Address - Kent Place School, Summit, N.J.; BBC Broadcast; Sermon at St. John's Chapel, Groton School;"The Christian World Mission in the Perspective of History;" Memorial Service for Dr. Thomas Cochrane;"The Church's Central Task"- given at Biblical Seminary Commencement;"Christian Frontiers;""Training an Indian Ministry;""The Constant Things;" Valedictory Service;"The Optimism of Grace;""The Word Became Flesh;""Challenge and Response;", 1950-1955 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - "World-Wide Evangelism in this Generation" Address for 2nd Assembly, World Council of Churches, Evanston, Illinois, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Settles Lectures - Austin Theological Seminary:"The Christian Mission in Faith and History;""The Heritage of History;""Contemporary Challenge;""Hope and Obedience" (and draft copies of each), 1956 Jan (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Address at dinner for Dr. Edward Willingham; "The Ministry of Memory;""No More Strangers and Foreigners;""Freedom in the Truth;""From Death to Immortality;""Some Ecumenical Fallacies;""Reflections on A Journey to Madagascar;" An Address at St. James Church, Gerrards Cross, 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Notebook, 1957, 1960, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Tripple Lecture - Drew University: Completed and Draft Copies:"John R. Mott: World Perspective";"Charles H. Brent: The Birth of an Idea";"Nathan Soderblom: Faith and Society";"William Temple: The Wholeness of the Task";"Vedanayagam Samuel Azariah: The Goal of a United Church", 1959 (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - "The Calling of the Missionary;" Worship Service; Inaugural Lecture -Drew University;"Yesterday Today and Tomorrow;" Address at Third Assembly of World Council of Churches; Address to Presbyterian Church in Ireland;"The Local and the Ecumenical" -- Address at Ranson's installation as President of Methodist Church in Ireland;"The Lordship of Christ;" Address to the Bradford Conference; Address at the Laymen's Fellowship;"How God Speaks to Man;" Methodist College Prize Distribution Speech, Ireland, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Notebook: Sermon Registry: Sermons and Addresses -- Ireland, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - "Time and Eternity;" BBC Morning Talks --"Lift Up Your Hearts;" Ulster Television Appearance -"End the Day;""Continuity and Change;" Drew Radio --"What Do You Mean;""Perspective on the Ecumenical Movement;""Ministerial Education Today;" Dinner in Honor of George W. Carpenter;"Manpower and Methodism;""Order of St. Luke", 1962-1965 (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - Fondon Lectures: Southern Methodist University: Patterns of Christian Unity:"The Given Reality;""The Promised Goal;""The Ecumenical Challenge;""The Primal Vision"; Mexico City 1963: Impressions of Meeting. of Commission on World Mission and Evangelism, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - New Jersey Area Methodist Ministers' Convocation:"The Context of Faith;""The Context of Worship", 1966 (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - The Commission on the Structure of Methodism Overseas: Adventurous Journey, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - The Commission on the Structure of Methodism, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - "Theology and the Higher Learning;""Sex and Marriage;""We Believe in Jesus Christ;""Four Decades of Missionary Cooperation;""The Continuing Presence;""Sacramental World"; Dedication Service;"Make Us Builders of Peace";"Thirty Years On: Change, and Continuity in Theological Education";"Harry J. Wieler", 1967-1976 (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Irish-British Journey"The Missionary Task", 1978 (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - "Fear and Love;""The Marks of a Christian;""the Gifts of the Spirit;""Grace and Truth;""The Choice of the Cross;""The Second Chance;""Jesus Christ: The Same Yesterday, Today, and For Ever;""The Biblical and Theological Basis of the Mission of the Church;""The Application of the Gospel to Modern Man;" (Box 5, Folder 105)
    - Sermon Notebook"The Ultimate Tragedy;""This is the Victory;""The Body of Christ;""The Heritage of Freedom;""I am a Debtor;", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - "God in National Life;" untitled;"A Visit to Germany;""The Collapse of Security;""Some Problems of Urbanization;""Raison D'etre (1) Mankind;" Synthesis: West on East;" Suggested Salutation for Week of Witness;"The Hope of a New World;""The Biblical and Theological Basis of the World Mission of the Church;""Spiritual; Values and the Second World War;""Theology and the Higher Education;""Hinduism: A Christian Approach;" (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - Sermon written in Tamil, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 108)
    - "A New Strategy for Missions;" notes;"History and the World Mission of the Church;""Make Us Builders of Peace;""Christianity and World Order;" illegible title;"The Epiphany;""The Grace of Christmas;""A Judging God;""The Family of God;"The Cultural and Vocational Aspects of Theological Education;" notes;"A Creative Ministry;""Is There Hope of a World Community;" (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - "Alive Unto God;" notes; Salisbury School Commencement;"How God Speaks to Man;""An Ecumenical Approach to Theological Education;" notes;"This is the Victory;""Lawrence J. MacGregor: In Memoriam;" Ella Bulchar: In Memoriam;""Richard Lighthall: In Memoriam;""Albert William Olsen: In Memoriam", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 110)
    - "Theology and the Christian Mission: An Historical and Biblical Approach;""In Search of the World;""Helen Clasper: In Memoriam;""Ministry in the Modern World;" Address at Hendrick's Chapel, Syracuse University;"Prospectives in Theological Education" (Box 6, Folder 111)
    - "Signs of the Times: the Rise of New Nations;" The Future of the I.M.C.;""The Christian Future in Eastern Asia;""The Christian World Mission: Its Source and Fulfillment;" lectures;"Apostolic Succession;""Wanted: Direction!""Words and The Word;""The Unchanging Christ;""The Charter of Unity;""The Constant Things;""Synthesis: West on East;""A New Peace;""Wesley's Conversion and the Needs of Today;" notes;"A Victorius Faith;" untitled;"The Transient and the Eternal;""Calling the Church to the World Mission Today;""World Without Books;""The Role of the Church;""A Valediction;""Comfort;""The Way of the Cross;""India - Today and Tomorrow;""Task of I.M.C.;""Living Issues;""The Church in India Guides Itself;""The Church in India Today;" (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - "What is Man?""Postwar Planning;" notes;"The Church in Changing India;" notes;"Special Thanksgiving;""Power;""Sanity;""The Triumphal Entry;""The Korean Crisis and the Future of Asia;""Training fot the Christian Ministry;""The World Mission of the Church;""Can We Still Believe in Christmas?""That They All Might Be One - That the World May Believe" (Box 6, Folder 113)
- Travel Diaries/ Notes, Series III
  - Geneva, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 114)
  - Asia, 1949-1950 (Box 7, Folder 115)
  - Madagascar, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 116)
  - Asia, Madagascar, 1956-1960 (Box 7, Folder 117)
  - "Asian Journey", 1959 (Box 7, Folder 118)
  - South Africa, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 119-120)
  - Tokyo, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 121)
  - Africa, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 122)
- Notes, Series IV
  - Notebooks (Box 8, Folder 123-124)
  - Coursework: Ecumenism (Box 8, Folder 125)
  - Coursework (Box 8, Folder 126)
  - Lecture Notes: India, Indonesia, Muslim World, Madagascar, and Africa (Box 8, Folder 127)
  - Coursework (Box 8, Folder 128)
  - Lecture Notes: Comparative Ecclesiology (Box 8, Folder 129)
  - Class notes on Ecumenism (Drew University ?) (Box 8, Folder 130-131)
  - Notes (Box 9, Folder 132-137)
- Organizations Served, Series V
  - Association of Methodist Theological Schools (AMTS), 1965-1967 (Box 10, Folder 138)
  - Conference on Theological Education in South East Asia" - Thailand, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 139)
  - Drew University - Installation, Contact Letters, 1959, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 140)
  - Drew University - Installation Addresses, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 141)
  - Drew University - Congratulatory Letters (Box 10, Folder 142-144)
  - Drew University - Installation Announcement Letter (Box 10, Folder 145)
  - Drew University - Installation: Greetings from Younger Churches (Box 10, Folder 146)
  - Drew University - Congratulatory Letters from an Album (Box 10, Folder 147)
  - Drew University - Coursework: Administrative (Box 10, Folder 148)
  - Drew University - Coursework: Comparative Ecclesiology Exam (Box 10, Folder 149)
  - Drew University - Coursework: STM Theses (Box 10, Folder 150)
  - Drew University - Coursework: Faculty Information (Box 10, Folder 151)
  - Drew University - Administrative: Budget (Box 10, Folder 152)
  - Drew University - Administrative: Minutes, Faculty Meetings, 1962-1964 (Box 10, Folder 153)
  - Drew University - Administrative: Minutes, Faculty Meetings, 1965-1967 (Box 10, Folder 154)
  - Drew University - Administrative: Dean Anderson's Report to Faculty (Box 11, Folder 155)
  - Drew University - Administrative: Budgets and Salaries (Box 11, Folder 156)
  - Drew University - Administrative: Items for Discussion With President (Box 11, Folder 157)
  - Drew University - Administrative: Budgets (Box 11, Folder 158)
  - Drew University - Administrative: Report to the President (Box 11, Folder 159)
  - Drew University - Administrative: Educational Policy Committee (Box 11, Folder 160)
  - Drew University - Administrative: Circuit Riders (Box 11, Folder 161)
  - Drew University - Administrative: Correspondence, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 162)
  - Drew University - Administrative (Box 11, Folder 163-164)
  - Drew University - Dismissal: Articles (Box 11, Folder 165)
  - Drew University - Dismissal: Articles, Circuit Riders (Box 11, Folder 166)
  - Drew University - Dismissal: Correspondence (Box 11, Folder 167)
  - Drew University - Dismissal: Correspondence With President (Box 12, Folder 168)
  - Drew University - Dismissal: Letters of Support (Box 12, Folder 169)
  - Drew University - Dismissal: Answered Correspondence (Box 12, Folder 170)
  - Drew University - Dismissal: Correspondence Records (Box 12, Folder 171)
  - Drew University - Dismissal: Faculty Letters to Trustees (Box 12, Folder 172)
  - Drew University - Dismissal:"Study of Control and Organization at Drew University" (Box 12, Folder 173)
  - Drew University - Dismissal: Acting Dean - Dr. Shippey, 1967-1968 (Box 12, Folder 174)
  - Drew University - Dismissal (Box 12, Folder 175-179)
  - Foundation for Theological Education in South East Asia (FTESEA); See Also: Record Group 31, 1968-1974 (Box 13, Folder 180)
  - Fund for Theological Education, 1968-1974 (Box 13, Folder 181)
  - Hartford Seminary Foundation; See Also: Drew University Files for Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 13, Folder 182)
  - Hartford Seminary Foundation - Advisory Commission to Board of Trustees, 1971-1972 (Box 13, Folder 183)
  - Hartford Seminary Foundation, 1971-1972 (Box 13, Folder 184)
  - Hartford Seminary Foundation - Proposals for Center for Religious Studies, 1971-1972 (Box 13, Folder 185)
  - Hartford Seminary Foundation, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 186)
  - Hartford Seminary Foundation - Academic Program Committee, 1976, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 187)
  - International Association for Mission Studies, 1970-1974 (Box 13, Folder 188)
  - International Missionary Council: NOTE: IMC correspondence is in Series I; Some documents without Ranson notation with placed with other IMC materials in the YDSL collection., 1947-1970, n.d (Box 13, Folder 189)
  - Irish Methodist Church, 1952, 1960-1963 (Box 13, Folder 190)
  - Irish Methodist Church - Presidency, 1958-1960, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 191)
  - Irish Methodist Church - Presidency, 1961-1963 (Box 14, Folder 192)
  - Irish Methodist Church, 1970, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 193)
  - Japan International Christian University Foundation, 1970-1973 (Box 14, Folder 194)
  - Japan International Christian University Foundation, Board of Directors - Annual Meeting, 1972, 1975 (Box 14, Folder 195)
  - National Council of Churches of Christ, 1956, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 196)